of
well
to me that he was the most clever home
trying to avoid her mister people's
belongs
molinaro
as you know sandy will approach the
mid-atlantic coast
later this weekend arts and he is very
likely to feel its effects
in the former high tides high winds and
heavy rainfall lasting for several days
well are going to be honest with you
said in the article was very scary
it was amazing to come believe that my
refrigerator was born in around like a
bowl
my bed my two cats had doctor
for into my mattress they want more
I was trying to pull them what they want
Kamau and our
we're just waiting for part about
bombing
use the work then there that was all
that respect
these are the only thing for white worms
for
government my warrior a reading of it
forward officials or
part pair my cousin
that if someone came along and offered
you a hundred thousand dollars
you better take your anything because
our house was work place right now
so when I heard about the bar down I was
thrilled part I will have to stay mad at
her
picking a hundred thousand dollars I'm
taking it just
moreover and then with the 22nd
people I signed the papers
on Thursday I just found out from you
that my old home demolish it's going to
be fair to fear
grow their own by actually gonna be
are more swampy area now order creek
running down the middle or
all the stuff from the house that I wore
starring the lot that were
from a lifetime of gathering up than
are very values just memories growing up
those will be the biggest things
and it was my first home
wanted the first neighborhoods are
people got together after the storm was
in Oakwood beach
on staten island where the residents
were already pretty organized because
they had organized a flood victims
committee in the neighborhood dating
back to 1982 and even before when they'd
been recurrently
flooded for many years they've been
waiting for better
storm protection and so before
there is even really a presence from
from the state
on the ground they're already talking
about what should we do actually rebuild
and so they decided that they wanted to
seek state buyout
so the a move it kinda federal buyout
programs
is to remove we're currently flooded
property is
and turn them back into open space so
the surname idea that you hear basically
you know moving back
from the waterfront in allowing places
to flood that will ideally make
make others safer and what's really
changed after sandy
is talking about this in terms of
longer-term adaptation to climate change
though it not only thinking about how do
we rebuild to be favor from the next
storm
but more about how do we have to change
everyday life
to be safer from things that are going
to get worse and worse and worse and
worse
this really for it to work people need
to
want to do it themselves that needs to
be initiated by the residents in these
areas given
all the barrels a living in an area like
this its it's not a good decision this
day
it's really not and in the only reason
you which day is because you just not
thinking clearly
we have a sentimental attachment that
you just can't break
I am with the leader of the Oakwood
beach by a committee
to three weeks after the storm II was
convinced there was no way
I was gonna never rebuild and I had to
just figure a way
have basically recouping my investment
and moving on
I learned about this program I spoke to
two different communities that have gone
through this program it's a federal
program
the government will buy out your home
but when they do is they give you the
priest on value
so on we put together our entire
proposal
we had including maps spreadsheet all
the homes blocking lot number
and a signature an acclimation from each
and every homeowner that name knew that
the program is voluntary
and that was voluntary and both sides
and they signed their names and their
interest
I was shocked because I knew that the
area the people that I was talking to
for those weeks
were brothers and sisters aunts uncles
grandmothers I said there's no way they
don't think this area
but they had it a day and an even to
this day I just spoke to one the people
on the committee
you know they all describe it as
bittersweet but she knows she just told
me last night it was the right decision
there's no way in the world
check even imagine living there again
all
I keep on fighting in I will fight them
and
as long as it stands I will fight them
in a war game
ass they want everybody else namely
they're gonna buy you out by
as far as people that own mortgages and
stuff like that and her over the head
and mortgages
really dozen really work out for them
type people like
by and behind in my mortgage
they wanted to give me 269,000 which
I'll 409,000
so was gone all the bank a difference
with nothing
you know nothing you know nothing Nolan
of I don't think it's about being really
care for people in its name
they don't really care they care about
pain the funds out again
over and over again when is a flight
and is a flood I got stuffed in the
basement lost this I lost that
gotta keep on paying fines is a way of
making money from the state
we still need help down here any it's
not over
and it's a lot of grief it's it's a lot
appoint hand
too thin forty-three is all along great
because all the sand
nation the mortgage company by the way
has been giving me a hard time
I came here three o'clock the guys were
in this house trying to lock up my whole
for the mortgage and now they tell me
the last hearing i you can get a
mortgage unless the house is renovated
but I have no money to renovate a house
the insurance money is to renovate a
house
you know give me the money to renovate
the house make and no one else
basically they doing everything it takes
to try to force me at his house
I'm not worried about the next to
lawmakers
I actually relocated most and pipes when
he was supposed to be an
and now relocated firmness I think
because I got everything up here
have nothing
I got to really like people I was nice
government
for all the homes that were girls
still have the neighborhood in Staten
Island at our first meeting in the
buyout program
there is Oakwood beach ocean breeze and
Grampy
its Oakwood beach in its total areas
over 400 parcels
I'm I love that in the majority a
purchases will happen where we actually
up structures we have homes there
so we're buying over 320 16-piece
parcels
and we rough finish acquisition this
neighborhood
in the next 12 months in with that mean
acquisition and demolition of all the
structures
I it would be another 18 months to
finish ocean breeze and probably another
twenty four months to complete Grand
Beach
I think there are challenges
at two having a broad stroke approach to
this hyper
strategic retreats on and so I think
that ambien is going to be a community
level interest in this
and and also you unfortunately
for Sun there's going to have to be
another catastrophic events
and to be able to recognize this
this impact in the fact that these these
are going to become more regular and
that we are going have
significant impacts from climate change
the long run
you were not used to this this is this
is a transformative moment
the storms are more ferocious and more
frequent
the science is very clear on that people
sometimes they think
aboul a storm and they say well we
shouldn't we shouldn't live
in a dense way we should live in a kind
more dispersed way and that's gonna
protect us during a storm
actually be officers true I think we
have enough density
to support kinda redundant systems and
more robust systems that are more
expensive but you're spreading
possible more people in a dense area you
actually have a long
resilience is just a question then
designing these buildings correctly
so we have a bunch buildings were
designing that are in the post and the
environment
a lot of that is about understanding
that sometimes these buildings will
flood
and when they flooded how will people
still use them
and I think words can actually get much
tougher is some other these more
more vulnerable areas are gonna flood
and then fled again and again and again
and it it is really all that the eastern
seaboard you can see
and I think it's going to get tougher
and tougher for us to be able to
societies day it's okay you know
have this many people get injured lose
their lives there's gonna be some way in
which
in these neighborhoods a really good to
reformulate
well
the Laura I is rising temperatures
at the global issue certainly by
when it happens in experience for you
what happens at a very local level so it
intersects with
vulnerabilities that already exist
locally people who are the most
vulnerable
in a particular neighborhood or city an
everyday level
they're going to have the hardest time
coping with the effects of this as well
as adopting
to climate change and I think there's
also urged going to look at it really
individually to look at a house by house
and think okay
you know this house you wanna buy out
yes or no but is a relief social
decisions you know things like after
after sandy there's a lot of talk lately
how do we protect lower Manhattan
because it has such a high concentration
of economic activity there so much well
and so you know lower Manhattan probably
won't have to do a measure tree
me there's going to be a lot of public
and private investment that prioritizes
protecting the appli- and so
the very political decision the end of
the day which places get protected which
places
have to move which places do residents
get a move on their own terms
which places people just gradually go
into foreclosure have to leave
you know who has the resources start
over again somewhere else who's given
assistance do that and who isn't
all those questions really are our
social
and political questions
Mike to move here
army to listen to require
and at night when it was very by hear
the waves
Berkshire it was really a common
affliction
fitness area are common
I could also tell when it was gonna rain
causes getaway splash in the ruling was
coming on its war
whatever the wave solder
rations